Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is עבודה זרה נ"ד,
Avodah Zarah Nundaled, עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 54. We pick up at
the very bottom of נ"ג עמוד ב', Nun Gimmel Amud Beis, and
we had just had a discussion about if a מזבח Mizbeach is
got chipped, נפגם, Nifgam, would that mean that automatically they would be
מבטל Mevatel it from its status of תשמישים, Tashmishim, and similarly the
story of a בימוס Bimos of a stand for an idol and
the opinions went both ways whether one opinion according even a בימוס
Bimos a little chip they stop using it but a מזבח Mizbeach
until it's totally destroyed or majority destroyed and the other did the
reverse that a בימוס Bimos has to be majority destroyed before they
stop using it but a מזבח Mizbeach even a little chip. Okay,
so we pick up at the bottom of נ"ג עמוד ב' Nun
Gimmel Amud Beis and two lines from the bottom, last three words
of the line, היכי דמי בימוס היכי דמי מזבח? Heichi dami Bimos
heichi dami Mizbeach? What is the difference between a בימוס Bimos stand
for an idol
and an altar? Now obviously they function different, but how do we
know by looking what we're looking at? So אמר רבי יעקב בר
אידי אמר רבי יוחנן בימוס אבן אחת מזבח אבנים הרבה. Ammar Rabbi
Yaakov bar Idi ammar Rabbi Yochanan Bimos even achas Mizbeach avanim harbeh.
A stand is one stone,
מזבח אבנים הרבה, Mizbeach avanim harbeh, and a מזבח, Mizbeach, an altar,
is made of many stones constructed together. Top of נ"ד עמוד א',
Nun Daled Amud Aleph, אמר
חזקיה מאי קרא? Ammar Chizkiyah mai krah? What's the פסוק Pasuk that
you both see that a מזבח Mizbeach is made out of many
stones and also supporting this idea that you need to destroy the
majority of it or the majority of it must be destroyed before
it's considered not usable and ביטול? Bitul? So בשומו כל אבני מזבח,
B'sumo kol avnei mizbeach, when God makes all of the stones of
the altar, so notice stones in plural, so we see it's many
stones, כאבני גיר מנופצות, K'avnei gir menupatzos, like shattered sandstone, לא יקומו
אשרים וחמנים, Lo yakumu asherim v'chammanim, they will not rise up
the
אשרים, Asherim, the trees that were worshipped and the sun images. איכא
כאבני גיר מנופצות, Ika k'avnei gir menupatzos, if it is shattered like
sandstone, you know it's really crumbled and basically totally
destroyed, לא יקומו אשרים וחמנים, Lo yakumu asherim v'chammanim, then they will
not use it anymore to worship and to bring offerings to the
אשרות Asheros and to the sun images. אלא, Ela, but if it's
not mostly shattered then they will still use it. Okay, so that's
showing you that it's made out of many stones and also that
it has to be majority shattered before they stop usage. תנו. Tnu.
Okay, now new point. That was really just wrapping up yesterday. נעבד
שלו אסר נעבד שלו אסר ושל חבירו מותר. Ne'evad shelo assar, ne'evad
shelo assar v'shelo chaveiro mutar.
If an animal is worshipped, it's not exactly clear how we know
it's talking about an animal, but that's anyway what the context is.
So if somebody worships an animal it's not forbidden for normal use
of a הדיוט, Hedyot, a normal use of a person,
but it does have a status of נעבד, Ne'evad, of an object
that was worshipped and it's אסור Assur for the מזבח. Mizbeach. Okay,
so this ברייתא Braisa tells us that if you if your own
thing, you worshipped your own thing, then you made it forbidden to
the מזבח, Mizbeach, but if you worshipped your friend's it does not
become forbidden because that's another principle which is you cannot make something
that isn't yours, you cannot make it forbidden. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says ורמינהי, V'ramini, I'll ask you on this, איזו נעבד
כל שעובדין אותו בין בשוגג בין במזיד בין באונס בין ברצון? Eizu
ne'evad kol she'ovdin oso bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid bein b'ones bein b'ratzon?
What is an animal that is considered worshipped, נעבד, Ne'evad, something that
has been worshipped and now can't be used again for the בית
המקדש? Bais Hamikdash? Anything that you worship it whether it's unintentionally or
willfully, whether it's forced or whether it's willful. רש"י Rashi sort of
says those phrases are the same, שוגג ומזיד Shogeg u'meizid more means
negligent and intentional whereas אונס ורצון Ones v'ratzon means it was against
your will or it was according to your will but they mostly
sort of describe the same circumstances. But we'll see what the גמרא
Gemara does when it zooms in on the word אונס. Ones. So
the גמרא Gemara says האי אונס היכי דמי? Hai ones heichi dami?
So what's the case when it says that you
worship this by force, you were forced to worship? לאו כגון דאנס
בהמת חבירו והשתחוה לה? Lav k'gon d'anas behemas chaveiro v'hishtachaveh lah? So
it assumes that the forcing was that you took
your friend's cow and you bowed down to it. Okay, so not
that you were forced, it's the נעבד. Ne'evad. What makes an animal
considered a נעבד Ne'evad that it cannot be used for the מזבח?
Mizbeach? So even if it was אונס Ones meaning even if the
animal was אונס Ones or even if the animal was taken against
the will of the owner. That's how it's reading it. So it
wants to read the אונס Ones there to tell you you can
give it that status even if it's your friend's
animal. So that's a proof against you. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר רמי בר חמא לא, Ammar Rami bar Chama lo, no, that's
not what it's talking about, כגון שאנסו עובדי כוכבים והשתחוו להם. K'gon
she'ansu avodei kochavim v'hishtachavu lahem. דידיה. didei.
No, no, no, it's not the animal that is being forced, it
is you that is being forced. The non-Jews basically put a gun
to your head and said bow down to this animal, your own
animal, so even though you were forced, and you might say that
it doesn't really constitute עבודה זרה, avoda zara, nevertheless the animal is
still considered to be נעבד ne'evad and forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Excuse
me, not forbidden in הנאה hana'ah but forbidden to the מזבח, mizbeach,
but it's talking about your own animal. And now we're going to
get into a fascinating discussion about the idea about being forced and
the יהרג ולא יעבור, yehareg v'lo ya'avor, which is a different question
from whether you were liable for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, right? Because,
okay, they were putting a gun to your head, so you were
supposed to give up your life, that's one of the things you're
supposed to martyr yourself for. You did not give up your life
and you bowed down to your animal. That does not make you
willful in the act of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you are still
אונס. ones. Guy's still holding a gun to your head. You have
actively chosen to not do the מצוה mitzvah of martyrdom, but in
the act of עבודה זרה avoda zara you are still אונס. ones.
All right, and therefore you might say, well, since that was forced
and not willful, maybe it doesn't make the animal forbidden? And the
חידוש chiddush is no, nevertheless the animal is forbidden. You know, what's
also interesting is it goes to a discussion in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about
whether העובד מאהבה ומיראה ha'oved me'ahava u'miyira is חייב chayav or not
for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. When the guy's holding a gun to
your head, not only are you an אונס, ones, is it really
עבודה זרה avoda zara if you're doing it out of fear and
you don't really believe in this? So again, there's that obligation to
give up your life, but when the guy's holding a gun to
your head, how much did you really do an act of עבודה
זרה? avoda zara? And here you did it under
compulsion and nevertheless the חידוש chiddush of this ברייתא, braita, the way
we're reading אונס, ones, is that it's still, the animal is still
נעבד ne'evad even though you are נאנס, ne'enas, the animal is still
נעבד. ne'evad. Okay, that's a very reasonable position. So let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
מתקיף לה רבי זירא, matkif lah Rabbi Zeira, Rabbi Zeira challenged this.
אונס רחמנא פטריה. ones rachmana patrei. What do you mean? An אונס
ones the Torah exempts you. דכתיב ולנערה לא תעשה דבר, dichitiv u'l'na'ara
lo ta'aseh davar, don't do anything to the woman who is raped,
it was not her fault. And that teaches a principle that if
something is perforce put on somebody, they have no liability. So it's
not exactly clear what the question is, you know, because okay, yes,
you know, you're not liable for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but who
says that the animal is still a נעבד? ne'evad? But you know,
the way תוספות Tosafot explains it, what really רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama is saying is that I consider that when you're forced,
it's like you didn't even do it. I mean that's a classic
question. Somebody that is נאנס, ne'enas, did he do it but he's
not liable, or do we say no, he was really like a
tool in the hand of the other person and therefore it's not
even as if he really did it? Okay, so רמי בר חמא
Rami bar Chama feels and maybe that's why he's quoting the פסוק
pasuk נערה לא תעשה דבר na'ara lo ta'aseh davar because if a
woman is being raped, you know, no matter how much she protests,
it can be done to her, so how much was she participating
in the act or and she says she was
participating in the act and she was exempt or is it saying
no it was an act of violence done to her she did
not do anything? So that seems to be his point and he
is saying that I can't even consider the animal to be a
נעבד ne'evad because you are an אונס. ones. Even if you should
have given up your life, you are an אונס, ones, so the
animal isn't a נעבד. ne'evad. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather Rava said,
הכל היו בכלל לא תעבדם. hakol hayu bichlal lo ta'avdem. All scenarios
were in the category of you shall not worship
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. וכשפירט לך הכתוב וחי בהם ולא שימות בהם,
uch'shepeiret lecha hakatuv v'chai bahem v'lo sheyamut bahem, and then the פסוק
pasuk says you know these are the מצוות mitzvot you should do
them, you should live by them, you know, which is the principle
that you do that if your life is at stake you go
ahead and you do the עבירה. avera. So okay, so I would
have said well if I apply וחי בהם v'chai bahem to עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, then if a guy's holding my gun to my
head a gun to my head I should do it. יצא אונס,
yatza ones, okay, that excludes an אונס ones that you're supposed to
go ahead and do it and I would have applied that even
to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. והדר כתב רחמנא ולא תחללו את שם
קדשי, ve'hadar katav rachmana v'lo techalelu et shem kodshi, but then it
says don't desecrate My name, which is the principle of קידוש השם
חילול השם Kiddush Hashem Chilul Hashem from which we learn that when
it comes to עבודה זרה avoda zara you even give up your
life, אפילו באונס. afilu be'ones. Okay, so what's the story? One פסוק
pasuk makes me think that by עבודה זרה avoda zara you don't
give up your life וחי בהם, v'chai bahem, the other makes me
think that you do give up your life. Now you could have
just said okay, you know, the ולא תחללו v'lo techalelu is telling
you that עבודה זרה avoda zara is an exception to וחי בהם.
v'chai bahem. But let's see what Rava says. So the גמרא Gemara
says הא כיצד הא בצינעא הא בפרהסיא. ha keitzad ha b'tzina ha
b'farhesia.
It's a difference between public and private. Now what does this mean?
Well, there is a position of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says
that the יהרג ולא יעבור yehareg v'lo ya'avor of עבודה זרה avoda
zara is only in public, which is like really, really a shock.
You know, sometimes we think if it's public and שעת השמד she'at
hashmad everything is יהרג ולא יעבור. yehareg v'lo ya'avor. Okay, there can
be public and not שעת השמד. she'at hashmad. But anyway, but רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says that the idea of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem
and חילול השם Chilul Hashem is in public. In private, you give
up, you know, you do the act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Okay, and it sounds like רבא Rava is agreeing with it. And
how would he therefore go back? He would, it sounds like he's
going back to רבי ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmiyah question and say,
excuse me, רב זירא's Reb Zeira question and saying, you're right, when
it was in private and it was אונס, ones, then it's not
like he did it because maybe I פוסק pasken like רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Ishmael, if it's in private you're supposed to go along and
do it. So since you were supposed to go along and do
it and the guy was holding a gun to your head, you
know, it's not like you did it and it doesn't make the
animal forbidden. Okay, when
that's רב זירא's Reb Zeira point. But רבא Rava says, when there
is a מצווה mitzvah of יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve'al ya'avor and
you're supposed to give up your life, ולא תחללו, velo techallelu, then
even if the guy's holding a gun to your head, you cannot
say you did not do the act. You were being told by
the תורה Torah that you are supposed to allow like, you know,
let yourself get killed, and you chose not to. So there, even
though there was a gun to your head and you were still
forced in the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, again, מזיד mazed in קידוש
השם, Kiddush Hashem, חילול השם, Chilul Hashem, but forced in the עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, that case you cannot say I didn't do it.
I did it, but I'm exempt because I was forced. But I
have to own doing it because I was supposed to have chosen
otherwise. So that's really a fascinating distinction between I didn't do it
and I did it but I'm exempt. I didn't do it because
I was basically the תורה Torah told me to listen to the
guy who's putting the gun to my head and therefore it's all
like he did it. I did it but I'm exempt is because
I wasn't supposed to listen to him. And that could explain, you
know, רב זירא Reb Zeira you're right when you're supposed, when you're
not supposed to give up your life, but when you're supposed to
give up your life, it does make it נעבד, ne'evad, even though
you were אונס ones in the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, so
that's like really a nice conceptual point. The only question is everybody
should be screaming, but just like what? You know, עבודה זרה avodah
zarah isn't יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve'al ya'avor in private? So a
whole big תוספות Tosfos here basically says, no no no, רבא Rava
clearly holds עבודה זרה avodah zarah is יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve'al
ya'avor in private. Even in private, he doesn't hold like רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Ishmael, you know, he's just here explaining according to רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Ishmael. What he's saying is even according to רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi
Ishmael approach, you know, I'll go with רב זירא's Reb Zeira idea
that you didn't do it, that I could see in עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it's not like you did it, according to רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael in private when you were supposed to listen. Okay, but
bottom line, you know, when you're supposed to give up your life,
which for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael is in public, and for us
it's whether public or private, when you're supposed to give up your
life, then you did it. Maybe you're exempt because you're forced, but
you, but you did it. Okay, so רבא's Rava just using רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael to distinguish between when you did, it's not like
you even did the act or when you did it and you're
exempt. But bottom line, it's very important for תוספות Tosfos to prove,
because so many Jews gave up their lives, you know, על קידוש
השם al Kiddush Hashem in the Middle Ages and at the time
of the Crusades, and not all the circumstances were a case of
public. And do we want to say they weren't supposed to give
up their lives? Do we really want to believe that there's no
martyrdom if it's, if it's in private, if it's only in public?
How could you say that? So it's very important, you know, ideologically,
religiously, for תוספות Tosfos to say that, and he proves it from
other גמרות, Gemaras, that רבא Rava holds you always are supposed to
give up your life. But we're just using it here to illustrate
the difference between did you do the act and are exempt and
then the animal is a נעבד, ne'evad, or it's like you didn't
even do the act at all and then the animal is not
a נעבד. ne'evad. I think what I should also say, you know,
which is
and it helps explain the idea of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that
you're supposed to worship עבודה זרה avodah zarah in private, right, is
that the situation that was sort of, you know, the Jews were
facing in the Middle Ages was different than the scenarios being talked
about in the גמרא. Gemara. In the scenarios in the גמרא, Gemara,
you do one act, you know, you bow down to an idol
and then you go on with your day and you're still Jewish,
and, you know, the non-Jew leaves you alone and then you go
on and then you keep שבת Shabbos and you do, you know,
and you keep כשר kosher and and everything is fine. Okay, you
just did this one act. So then you could have somebody say,
well, if it was one act, then in private, you know, and
you don't even really believe in the עבודה זרה avodah zarah or
whatever, maybe you shouldn't be giving up your life. In תוספות's Tosfos
scenario, you were being asked to convert. Okay, and that was very
different. When you're asked to convert, you could say even in private
is a complete renunciation of your identity and that would be יהרג
ואל יעבור. yehareg ve'al ya'avor. Anyway, תוספות Tosfos does not make that
distinction. Okay, let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. אמרו ליה רבנן
לרבא. Amru lei rabanan le-Rava. So the Rabbis said to רבא, Rava,
תניא דמסייע לך. tanya demisaye'a lach. There's a ברייתא Baraita that supports
you that sometimes, you know, the thing really can be נעבד. ne'evad.
אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
what is it? דמסייע במשאות של עובדי כוכבים. demisaye'a bi-massaot shel ovdei
kochavim.
So if you have these, again, these like platforms of the non-Jews.
בשעת הגזירה, Besha'at hagezeirah, and it's at a time when they're trying
to get rid of the Jewish religion, so it's a time of
שמד, shmad, and everybody's being forced to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
אף על פי שהגזירה בטילה, Af al pi hagezeirah bateilah, even when
now that the גזירה gezeirah has passed and Jews can go on
living their lives, okay, אותן בימוסאות לא בטלו *osan bimusa'os lo batlu*.
Those things remain אסור asur *asur*. So you see, this is going
not like רב זירא *Rav Zeira* who wanted to claim that by
אונס *ones* it doesn't become אסור asur *asur*. Here's a case of
אונס *ones* and it became אסור asur. *asur* and that proves like
you and it proves like who is the one who said it
before, רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* was it? רמי בר חמא
*Rami
bar Chama*. Okay, so this proves to you that yes, even when
you are forced it becomes אסור *asur*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this, לא בטלו *lo batlu*. אמר להו *Amar lehu*. So
he says so, רבא *Rava* said back to the rabbis who tried
to support him, אי משום הא לא תסייע *ei mishum ha lo
tesaye*. That doesn't really prove my point. And why? אימא ישראל מומר
הוה ופלח ליה ברצון *eima Yisrael mumar havah u'falach lei b'ratzon*. At
a time when they're trying to wipe out the religion and they're
threatening to kill people, so these altars might not have been, might
have been worshipped not just by people under the threat of death.
There might be Jews that were willing to basically go along, say,
why I'm not sticking around with being part of the Jewish people
anymore, like it's too dangerous. So they sort of willingly participate, not
just on the threat of death. So you can't prove where that
those were only cases of being worshipped by force. So רב אשי
*Rav Ashi* אמר *amar*, לא תימא אימא אלא ella, ודאי ישראל מומר
הוה ופלח ליה ברצון *lo teima eima ella vadai Yisrael mumar havah
u'falach lei b'ratzon*. You shouldn't say maybe, in those scenarios there will
always be some Jew that's doing it willingly. Okay, so you can't
prove from that. But this is a fascinating case of when you
are נאנס *ne'enas* to worship עבודה זרה avoda zarah, *avodah zarah*, is
it seen like you've done the action and does the animal consider
a נעבד ne'evad. *ne'evad*? Now back to all of that was to
answer how can you make something forbidden that is not your animal
because we thought אונס *ones* first meant that you were forcing, it
was against the will of the owner, and we switched it to
say you are the one being forced. But now we're going to
go back to our original reading. חזקיה *Chizkiyah* אמר *amar*, no, חזקיה
*Chizkiyah* says no, the ברייתא *braisa* is what we thought it meant.
You were worshipping the, אונס *ones* was the animal or the owner
of the animal. You were worshipping the animal against the will of
the owner. So what about the point that you're not, you can't
make something forbidden that isn't yours? So חזקיה *Chizkiyah* אמר *amar*, כגון
שניסך לעבודת כוכבים יין על קרניה *kegon she'nisach l'avodas kochavim yayin al
karneha*. No, what you did is you didn't just worship it, you
did an action to it. And this is the principle that even
though אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו *ein adam oser davar she'eino
shelo*, you can't by bowing down or whatever make something forbidden that
isn't yours because you don't have control over it to change its
status. If you actually do something physical to it, then you can
change its status even if you haven't physically changed it. So yes,
that means אונס *ones* means that you actually against the will of
the owner you used this animal to worship עבודה זרה avoda zarah.
*avodah zarah*, you poured wine between its horns in your worship of
the בעל *Ba'al* or whatever, and that makes it forbidden. Okay, so
because that's an actual action. מתקיף לה רב אדא בר אהבה *Mas'kif
lah Rav Adda bar Ahava*. So רב אדא בר אהבה *Rav Adda
bar Ahava* asks on this, הי נעבד ne'evad *hai ne'evad*? That's not
a case, no, we're discussing something that is נעבד *ne'evad*, worshipped and
therefore אסור *asur* to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. הי
בימוס בעלמא הוא *hai bimus b'alma hu*. If all you're doing is
pouring wine on it, you're using it like a type of a
stand, an altar, you're using it as a תשמיש tashmish *tashmish* of
עבודה זרה avoda zarah, *avodah zarah*. A תשמיש *tashmish*, an animal that
was a תשמיש *tashmish* of עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* isn't
אסור *asur* to the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbeach*. The only thing that's אסור
*asur* to the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbeach* of an animal is, because animals
can't really become עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* itself, but they
become נעבד *ne'evad*, but only if it's a נעבד *ne'evad*. Something like
this used as a תשמיש *tashmish* does not become forbidden. Okay, so
he says הי בימוס בעלמא הוא ושרי *hai bimus b'alma hu v'shari*
and it's permissible. Now some say some have a different גרסא *girsa*,
בימוס בעלמא הוא דשוייה *bimus b'alma hu deshavyei*. He only made it
a בימוס *bimus* and it's not making a claim as to whether
a בימוס *bimus* would be אסור *asur* to the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeach*
or not, if an animal that was a בימוס *bimus*, but it's
just saying that's not the scenario. The scenario we're talking about is
נעבד *ne'evad* and you just gave us a scenario of using it
like a type of an altar. So אלא אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה *ella amar Rav Adda bar Ahava*, fine, let's adjust that a
little bit. כגון שניסך לה יין בין קרניה *kegon she'nisach lah yayin
bein karneha*. No, you poured wine between its horns to worship it,
the animal itself. Fine, okay, so you got me. I was a
little imprecise. But the point still is that yes, that is a
case where you can make somebody's animal forbidden even though it's against
the will of the owner, if you did an action to it
in your act of worshipping it, you did an action to it.
דעבד בה מעשה ma'aseh, *de'avad bah ma'aseh* that you did an action.
So now we've introduced that you can make something of your friend's
forbidden if you do an action to it. וכי הא דאתא עולא
Ulla *v'chi ha d'asa Ulla*, and like when עולא Ulla, *Ulla* came
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan,
*amar Rabbi Yochanan*, he said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabi
Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, אף על פי שאמרו משתחוה לבהמת חבירו mishtachaveh livahemat
chaveiro. לא אסרה asrah *af al pi she'amru mishtachaveh l'vehemas chaveiro lo
asrah*. Here it's going, even though now we're talking about if you
bow down to your friend's animal you did not make it forbidden,
again, forbidden to the מזבח *mizbeach*, right? Because this is again an
animal can't be forbidden to lay people, an animal that was worshipped.
But even though when you bow down to your friend's animal you
do not make it. make it forbidden to the מזבח because it's
not yours, עשה בה מעשה אסרה. Asah bah ma'aseh asrah. If you
did an action to it, a physical act to it, then you
are exerting control on it, and then you can change its status
and make it forbidden to the מזבח. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar
lei Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said when he was
told that this is what עולא reported, פוק ואמרו ליה לעולא, Puk
ve'imru lei le'Ulla, go back and say to עולא, כבר תרגמה רב
הונא לשמעתיך בבבל. Kevar tirgemah Rav Huna lishma'atich beVavel. רב הונא Rav
Huna already taught your teaching essentially in בבל. Bavel. You came from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and a big teaching in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan and we already heard that more or less
from רב הונא Rav Huna in בבל. Bavel. Why? What did רב
הונא Rav Huna say? דאמר רב הונא, De'amar Rav Huna, because רב
הונא Rav Huna said, three lines from the bottom, הייתה בהמת חבירו
רבוצה בפני עבודת כוכבים, Hayetah behemt chaveiro revutzah bifnei avodat kochavim, if
your friend's animal was
crouched down in front of an idol, so you didn't even push
it down, it was already crouched down, כיון ששחט בה סימן אחד
אסרה, Keivan sheshachat bah siman echad asrah, and you took your knife
and even though you didn't yet do a full שחיטה, shechitah, so
you didn't actually make it like a זבח, zevach, because you didn't
do a full שחיטה, shechitah, you just did a little cut, you
cut only one of the סימנים, simanim, only the trachea or the
esophagus, that was enough to still make it forbidden. Now, this is
not exactly the same. Why is it not the same? Because we're
not talking
about a נעבד. Here the animal is being used as a תקרובת
tikrovet for the עבודה זרה, avoda zara and we're talking about making
it forbidden to a הדיוט, hedyot, because it's actually being offered as
a תקרובת tikrovet and it's being killed, so it's not staying in
sort of the status of an animal and it's going to be
forbidden to everybody. Nevertheless, the תוספות Tosafot discusses all those differences, but
תוספות Tosafot basically says, okay, but the relevant point is, even though
you normally can't make somebody else's thing forbidden, when you actually go
ahead and do a physical act to it, you can make it
forbidden. Now, again,
you would say even that, maybe pouring wine between the horns is
not as much of a physical act as slitting its throat, which
is actually changing the thing itself. So, it still is,
I think the חידוש chiddush of any act on it makes it
forbidden is bigger
than what רב הונא Rav Huna said here, which is actually when
you were שוחט shochet it, that makes obviously even a little more
obvious that that would change its status. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, מנלן דאסרה. Menalan de'asrah. Now that we've all very
good, everybody wants to take credit for who taught this thing, that
when you do an act you make it forbidden even if it's
not yours. But where do we learn this principle from? אילימא מכהני,
Eileima mikahanei, so we're going back to what we taught two days
ago, that the כהני kahanei who
served
in בית חוניו Beit Chonyo were prohibited
from serving in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash which is of course
crazy. It's not like an object that's a נעבד or
תשמישיו, tashmishav, it's a completely different thing, it's just a קנס. knas.
But okay, the גמרא Gemara wanted to just get us back to
that.
ודילמא שאני כהני דבני דעה נינהו. Udilma shani kahanei debnei de'ah ninhu.
They have intellect and they were fined. It's really not relevant for
us. It's very, very not relevant for us. ואלא, Ve'ela, let's get
to a better case, מאבני מזבח, Me'avnei Mizbeach, which was part of
the previous discussion, so maybe that's how the גמרא Gemara came into
it through
כהני. kahanei. The stones of the altar that when the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash was taken over by the Greeks, the Seleucids, whatever,
they had to, and then the
חשמונאים Chashmonaim retook it and we had miracle of Hanukkah, then they
had to dispose of the stones of the מזבח. Now, how were
they forbidden?
How could the Greeks make it forbidden? Even if they worshipped it
or whatever they did to it, they didn't own it. It's משתחוה
לבהמת חבירו. mishtachaveh levehemat chaveiro, So, it must be that the only
way they made it forbidden, it must be that there is this
principle that you can do that even if you are, as long
as you do a מעשה, an act to the thing itself. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, ודילמא כדרב פפא, udilma kederav Pappa, maybe
that is like רב פפא Rav Pappa that said earlier when we
were discussing this that there was a פסוק, pasuk, ובאו בה פריצים
וחיללוה, uva'u vah pritzim vechilliluha, that when they enter in, they desacralize
it and then it becomes ownerless and they took ownership of it,
so it really wasn't like it was owned by the בית המקדש
anymore and that's why it could work. But maybe the general principle
still is, if it's your friend's thing and somebody else's thing, you
cannot make it forbidden even if you do an act. So let's
look at the top of נ"ד
ע"ב. Nun Daled Amud Bet. ואלא מכלים. Ve'ela mikeilim. So again, this
is all echoing back the סוגיא sugya we had two days ago,
it's the case about the vessels that were used at the time
of חזקיהו Chizkiyahu that אחז, Achaz, that were put away when אחז
Achaz had used for עבודה זרה. avoda zara דכתיב, Dechtiv, כל הכלים
אשר הזניח המלך אחז במלכותו במעלו. kol hakeilim asher hizniach haMelech Achaz
bemalkhuto bema'alo. So all the vessels that the king אחז Achaz despised
of in his kingship, במעלו, bema'alo, when he trespassed and used them
for עבודה זרה, avoda zara הכינו והקדשנו. hikhinu vehikdashnu. We prepared them
and sanctified them. And what does that mean? ואמר מר, Ve'amar mar,
as we taught two days ago,
הכינו שגנזום, hikhinu sheganzum, that
we
hid them. דהא אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו de-ha ein adam
oser davar she-eino shelo אלא כיון דעביד בהו מעשה ela keivan de-avid
behu ma'aseh since he used them actually physically used them in the
עבודה זרה avoda zara איתסרו להו itsru lehu he made it forbidden
הכא נמי כיון דעבד בהו מעשה אסר hacha nami keivan de-avad behu
ma'aseh asar here too the same would be again even though there
it's really אסור even for like a layperson it was ממש תשמישי
עבודה זרה mamash tishmishei avoda zara in a vessel and here we're
talking about an animal for the מזבח the principle is that that
idea that you can't make something forbidden if it's not yours if
you do something physically to it you can. Okay now כי אתא
רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabi Yochanan
now when because we're talking about teachings in the name of רבי
יוחנן Rabi Yochanan relating to עבודה זרה avoda zara so we're going
to say some others. When רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said in the name of רבי יוחנן אף
על פי שאמרו המשתחוה לקרקע עולם לא אסרה af al pi she-amru
ha-mishtachaveh le-karka olam lo asrah even though the principle is that you
know if you bow down to like a mountain you know something
that's part of the nature you can't make it
forbidden so same idea like you can't make your friend's thing forbidden
but then there was an exception you know if you did an
action. So here too there's going to be an exception חפר בה
בורות שיחין ומערות chafar ba borot shichin u-mearot if you dug like
wells and cisterns אסרה you made it forbidden because you actually physically
changed it. Now what did you make forbidden? Like what if I
go ahead and I dig a well in the side of a
mountain and I worship the whole mountain I can make the whole
mountain forbidden? Presumably not. Presumably it's like the well is considered my
thing and I made the well forbidden.
So that seems to be what he is saying that קרקע עולם
karka olam is something that's like not under your control the same
way like an animal isn't under your control and it can't be
therefore that's why an animal can't be forbidden to a normal layperson
just because it was worshipped you know something that's your friend's that
you don't own isn't your control you made it a little more
under your control that thing that you controlled that well that you
dug that you can make forbidden. כי אתא רב שמואל בר יהודה
אמר רבי יוחנן ki ata Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda amar Rabi Yochanan
now שמואל בר יהודה Shmuel bar Yehuda came he said in the
name of רבי יוחנן אף על פי שאמרו המשתחוה לבעלי חיים לא
אסרן af al pi she-amru ha-mishtachaveh le-ba'alei chayim lo asaran now that's
now it's exactly that. So we dealt with an exception to the
rule of something you don't own an exception to the rule of
you know part of the
landscape קרקע עולם karka olam and now we're going to be exception
to the rule of the animal. Even though we say that if
you bow down to an animal you do not make it forbidden
to a
layperson עשאן חליפין לעבודת כוכבים אסרן asaan chalifin la-avodat kochavim asaran so
we already said that in addition if you do an act to
it so we're not going to discuss that we're going to discuss
a different point. If you went ahead and sold and you know
sold an idol and and you know got this animal in its
stead so then that animal gets the אסור בהנאה asur be-hana'ah status
of the idol. Not because you know not because what do you
call not because it's something that's considered worshipped or תשמיש or whatever
it's just actual you know it's not an עבודה זרה avoda zara.
but it was payment for an עבודה זרה avoda zara and therefore
it gets the same איסור isur status that the עבודה זרה avoda
zara had. And now we're going to introduce that idea that money
that was paid for עבודה זרה avoda zara I mean we had
it way back in like the first and second פרק perek but
anyway money that was paid for an עבודה זרה avodah zarah, is
אסור like עבודה זרה. avodah zarah Okay
כי אתא רבין אמר ki ata Ravin amar when רבין Ravin came
from ארץ ישראל he said פליגו בה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי ורבנן
pligu ba Rabi Yishmael bereibi Yosi ve-rabanan it's a debate of רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabi Yishmael bereibi Yosi and the rabbis. חד אמר
חליפין אסורין chad amar chalifin asurin that the initial money that was
paid for that was used to pay for an עבודה זרה avodah
zarah is forbidden חליפי חליפין מותרין chalifei chalifin mutarin but let's say
you know I take the twenty dollars that I got for selling
my עבודה זרה avodah zarah. whatever and I go ahead and I
buy some apples with it. So those twenty that cash that twenty
dollars or those twenty dollars in coins remain forbidden okay but now
what about the apples the stuff I bought with it does the
איסור isur keep on transferring? So he says one opinion is that
that's already permissible. וחד אמר אפילו חליפי חליפין נמי אסורין ve-chad amar
afilu chalifei chalifin nami asurin no even two degrees removed is forbidden.
מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר חליפי חליפין נמי אסורין mai ta'ama de-man de-amar
chalifei chalifin nami asurin what's the reason of the one that says
two degrees is forbidden we haven't figured out yet why one degree
is forbidden but okay אמר קרא amar kra because the פסוק pasuk
says והיית חרם כמוהו ve-hayita cherem kamo-hu right you know you shall
abominate the עבודה זרה avodah zarah lest you be חרם cherem like
something put under the ban just like it. So from there we
learn כל שאתה מהייה ממנו kol she-ata mehaye mimenoh anything that you
sort of create from it bring about as a result of it
so anything that's sort of coming you know in its stead so
the money is coming in its stead הרי הוא כמוהו harei hu
kamo-hu it's like it and it's forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Okay so
that's the פסוק pasuk that teaches you that the money gets the
status but it's but the דרשה drasha of anything that comes in
its stead כל kol you know maybe the חרם cherem has a
sense of absolute from there he learns even the second degree presumably
even the third and fourth and fifth. ואידך ve-idach what would the
other one say?
אמר קרא הוא. amar kra hu. It says והיית חרם כמוהו ve-hayita
cherem kamo-hu like it so it has to be connected to the
first. itself. So only the immediate money that was paid, not another
degree removed. ואידך ve'idach *ve'idach* so what would the one who goes
ad infinitum say? ההוא מיבעי ליה למיעוטי ערלה orlah וכלאי הכרם *hahu
miba'ei lei l'ime'utei orlah v'kilayei hakerem*. No, no, no, the כמוהו *kamo
hu* is saying this principle that the money paid for it gets
its status only applies to עבודה זרה avodah zarah *avodah zarah*, it
doesn't apply to other things that are אסור בהנאה *assur b'hana'ah* like
ערלה *orlah*, you know, first three years or כלאי הכרם *kilayei hakerem*,
you know, you cross-bred, you know, grain with wine. Okay, so those
things are אסור בהנאה *assur b'hana'ah*, but this והיית חרם כמוהו *v'hayisa
cherem kamo hu*, this idea that the thing is under the ban
and anything that comes from it is forbidden, that's just for עבודה
זרה avodah zarah *avodah zarah*. It is not for other איסורי הנאה
*issurei hana'ah*. But this opinion still says with עבודה זרה avodah zarah
*avodah zarah* it goes ad infinitum. Okay, שאם מכרן וקידש בדמיהן *she'im
machran
v'kidesh bidmeihen*, if you sold כלאי הכרם *kilayei hakerem* or ערלה *orlah*
and then you used it to marry a woman, מקודשת *mekudeshet*, she's
married. Okay, the money doesn't have a status of איסורי הנאה *issurei
hana'ah*. If you give a woman איסור issur הנאה *issur hana'ah* for
כסף קידושין *kesef kiddushin*, it doesn't have value and she's not married.
This money does not have the status of איסורי הנאה *issurei hana'ah*.
Now רש"י *Rashi* says you're it's still אסור *assur* for you to
do it because by using the money for your כסף קידושין *kesef
kiddushin* you're getting הנאה *hana'ah*, okay, but anyway that's somewhat of a
question, but nevertheless the money is not איסור הנאה *issur hana'ah* when
it does not get the status by things that are not עבודה
זרה *avodah zarah*. ואידך *ve'idach* and the other one would say ערלה
וכלאי הכרם לא צריכי מיעוטא *orlah v'kilayei hakerem lo tzrichi mi'uta*. No,
no, no, I didn't need כמוהו *kamo hu* to exclude ערלה *orlah*
and כלאי הכרם *kilayei hakerem*. Why? דהוו להו עבודה זרה ושביעית שני
כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין *d'havu lehu
avodah zarah u'shevi'is shenei kesuvim haba'im k'echad v'chol shenei kesuvim haba'im k'echad
ein melamdin*. Because the idea that the status transfers is said by
עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* as we just quoted, and I'll show you
that it's said by שמיטה shmitah *shemitah* produce as well. And therefore
if the תורה *Torah* teaches you in two places, if it taught
you one place, maybe that one place is a paradigm and you're
supposed to apply it to everything, but if it says the same
הלכה halachah *halacha* in two cases, it must be those two cases
are an exception. So that's the principle of שני כתובים הבאים כאחד
אין מלמדין *shenei kesuvim haba'im k'echad ein melamdin*. If it told you
it not just once but twice, then you should infer from that
it's an exception and it's not the rule. So from the fact
that it says it by עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* and שמיטה shmitah
*shemitah*, I know that the rule is the opposite, that the status
does not transfer. And that's therefore I do not need כמוהו *kamo
hu* to limit ערלה *orlah* and כלאים *kilayim* and כמוהו *kamo hu*
tells me just the first generation. Okay, and now we're going to
look at שמיטה *shemitah*. עבודת כוכבים הא דאמרן *avodas kochavim ha d'amran*,
עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* we said. שביעית *shevi'is* שמיטה *shemitah* דכתיב *dichsiv*
the פסוק *pasuk* says כי יובל היא קדש תהיה לכם *ki yovel
hi kodesh tihyeh lachem*. It is יובל *yovel*, it shall be holy
to you. Now where יובל *yovel* and שמיטה *shemitah* have the same
laws of not working the land and that the fruit gets קדושה
Kedushah *kedusha*, so even though we're looking about יובל *yovel*, we're assuming
that this is a general truth about the קדושת שביעית *kedushas shevi'is*
שמיטה *shemitah*. מה קדש תופס את דמיו ואסור *mah kodesh tofes es
damav v'assur*, so it says it's קודש *kodesh*. The same way we
know from other פסוקים psukim *psukim* in the תורה *Torah* that when
an animal has a blemish you transfer the sanctity to the money,
so the same way we know by הקדש *hekdesh* when there's an
exchange for money, the status transfers, אף שביעית תופסת את דמיה ואסורה
*af shevi'is tofeset es dameha v'assura*, even שמיטה *shemitah*, if you sell
שמיטה *shemitah* produce, then the money that was used to buy it,
that status transfers to the money itself. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says one minute, that's not exactly, so we learn it from
קודש *kodesh*, okay, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says wait, but that's
not how קודש *kodesh* works. אי מה קודש תופס את דמיו ויוצא
לחולין *ei mah kodesh tofes es damav v'yotze l'chullin*, when the status
transfers to money by like a קרבן *korban* that has a מום
*mum*, that's because you're removing the sanctity, putting it on the money,
and the קרבן *korban* is now no longer sanctified. אף שביעית תופסת
את דמיה ויוצאת לחולין *af shevi'is tofeset es dameha v'yotzes l'chullin*? So
if you're saying that שמיטה *shemitah* food is like קודש *kodesh* and
that the status transfers to the money, then maybe the produce itself
now stops being שמיטה *shemitah*? That's not true. תלמוד לומר תהיה *talmud
lomar tihyeh*, קדש תהיה לכם *kodesh tihyeh lachem*. So קודש *kodesh* tells
me that the money gets the status and תהיה *tihyeh* tells me
but the status never leaves the original fruit. בהוייתה תהא *b'havayasa teha*,
it should remain in its original status. הא כיצד *ha keitzad*, how
does this work? לקח בפירות שביעית בשר *lakach b'peiros shevi'is basar*, let's
say you swapped for your שמיטה *shemitah* produce meat, אלו ואלו מתבערים
בשביעית *elu v'elu misba'arim b'shevi'is*. So now the original קדושה Kedushah *kedusha*
never leaves the original שמיטה *shemitah* produce, let's say the grain, and
it also though goes onto the meat, and the meat has קדושת
שביעית *kedushas shevi'is*, and one of the things that means other than
you have to eat it is you have to eat it by
a certain time before what's called the period of ביעור *biur*, of
when the things have to get destroyed. Okay, לקח בבשר דגים *lakach
b'vasar dagim*, now you swapped the meat for fish, יצא בשר נכנסו
דגים *yatza basar nichnesu dagim*. Okay, so the קדושה Kedushah *kedusha* goes
from the meat to the fish. Okay, בדגים יין *b'dagim yayin*, you
swapped the fish for wine, יצאו דגים נכנס יין *yatz'u dagim nichnas
yayin*. ביין שמן *b'yayin shemen*, and then with the wine oil, יצא
יין ונכנס שמן *yatza yayin v'nichnas shemen*. הא כיצד *ha keitzad*, what's
the basic rule? אחרון אחרון נתפס בשביעית Acharon acharon nitpas bashevi'is *acharon
acharon nitpas b'shevi'is*, the very last one, you know, the... קדושה Kedushah
that that the original transaction made the קדושה go, it stayed on
the original fruit, but it made קדושה go to the thing, to
the thing that was swapped, and that קדושה of the thing that
was swapped keeps on traveling every time you do another swap, and
then it gets, you know, and it stays on the last thing
it was swapped for. So אחרון אחרון נתפס בשביעית ופרי עצמו אסור
upri atzmo asur and the original thing though remains אסור. Okay, so
therefore since this idea that something becomes קדוש, kadosh, you know, is
learned from, you know, שמיטה he says, then, I mean excuse me,
that the thing that's swapped becomes קדוש, kadosh, I have it by
שמיטה and by
עבודה זרה, therefore I can use the כמהו kamohu to tell me
only first generation, not second generation. Okay, so ואידך the other one
would say קסבר שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין kasavar shnei kesuvim
haba'im ke'echad ein melamdin ואיצטריכו לתרווייהו. ve'itztarchu letarveihu. No, even two פסוקים
they might be the rule and not the exception and I would
have used them as the rule. So כמהו kamohu is telling me
not ערלה and כלאיים, kilayim, but yes the קדושה keeps on or
the איסור of עבודה זרה keeps on ad infinitum. Okay, so that
was the הלכה about, you know, exceptions, basically this whole idea of
משתחוה לבהמת חבירו, you can't make it forbidden, but then exceptions about
if you do an action to it and exceptions to קרקע עולם
karka olam and now an exception to if you use the animal
to swap for an עבודה זרה itself. Okay, now we move on
to the next משנה, mishnah, this is really like the last משנה
mishnah in the discussions of עבודה זרה. From after this משנה mishnah
the גמרא Gemara on, it's all going to be about יין נסך.
yayin nesech. So let's take a look. And the גמרא ends or
this, you know, this section of the גמרא ends with a more
philosophical reflection.
So שאלו את הזקנים ברומי, shalu es hazekenim beRomi, the elders, the
Jewish elders were asked in Rome, אם אין רצונו בעבודת כוכבים, im
ein retzono ba'avodas kochavim, you, you believe in God and you believe
all these idols are nonsense. So if your God doesn't want all
these idols, למה אינו מבטלה? lamah eino mevatlah? So, you know, it's
funny before we talked about a עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, a non-Jew
being מבטל mevatel the עבודה זרה of a עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim,
you know, a Jew can't be מבטל mevatel the עבודה זרה of
a עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, the same word of מבטל. mevatel. But
why does God not destroy the עבודה זרה from the world if
he's so against it?
אמרו להן amru lahen they said back to them, אילו דבר שאין
צורך העולם בו היו עובדים היה מבטלה. ilu davar she'ein tzorech ha'olam
bo hayu ovdim hayah mevatlah. If people would worship things that there
was not needed for the world, God would destroy it. הרי הן
עובדים, harei hen ovdim, but look at what people worship, לחמה ללבנה,
lachamah lalevanah, the sun, the moon, לכוכבים, lakochavim, the stars, ומזלות, umazalos,
the, you know,
the
constellations. יאבד עולמו מפני השוטים? ye'aved olamo mipnei hashotim? Should God destroy
his world? Like he destroys everything that people worship? You know, he's
destroying things that he created just because they're idiots that do these
things, that's not why, that's not, God is not going to come
and destroy them and that will hurt the world. אמרו להן אם
כן יאבד דבר שאין צורך לעולם ויניח דבר שצורך לעולם. amru lahen
im kein ye'aved davar she'ein tzorech le'olam veyaniach davar shetzorech le'olam. Okay,
so why doesn't God just destroy the things that are, like, you
know, like all the statues? Fine, don't destroy the sun and the
moon and the stars. But if the statues are an offense to
God that are worshiped, why doesn't God at least destroy those? The
world doesn't need those. אמרו להן amru lahen so the sages said
back, אף אנו מחזיקים ידי עובדיהם של אלו. af anu machzikim yedei
ovdeihem shel elu. No, even we or meaning even God would be
strengthening the people that worship the sun and moon and the stars.
אומרים תדעו שאין אלוהות שהרי הן לא בטלו. omerim tedu she'ein elohos
sheharei hen lo batlu. They would see that, you know, that all
of the statues were destroyed and the sun and moon and stars
are still there, so they wouldn't say, look God is true, they
would say look our עבודה זרה is true. Alright, so that's their
answer, but you know you have to, it's also like look, it
also a little bit echoes, you know, you're living in this pagan
world, this world of temptations, this world, sometimes hostile world, right, that's
what so much of the מסכת masechet is about. And to some
degree there's also this question, like, you know, if they're powerful and
they're dominant, maybe they're right, you know. So and, you know, and
maybe these actually were philosophical discussions that happened, you know, between the
sages and Roman philosophers, but maybe it's also trying to respond to
a feeling like a Jew might have, you know, like how do
I explain why these things are proliferating, why doesn't God doing something
about it if they're such an offense to God. Okay, so let's
see what the גמרא says. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, שאלו פלוסופין את
הזקנים shalu filosofin es hazekenim ברומי. beRomi. אם
אלוהיכם אין רצונו בעבודת כוכבים. im eloheichem ein retzono ba'avodas kochavim. So
this is similar to the משנה mishnah but it actually will introduce
another element. אם אלוהיכם אין רצונו בעבודת כוכבים, im eloheichem ein retzono
ba'avodas kochavim, if your God doesn't want idols, מפני מה אינו מבטלה?
mipnei mah eino mevatlah? אמרו להם amru lahem they said back, אילו
דבר שאין העולם צריך לו היו עובדים הרי הוא מבטלה. ilu davar
she'ein ha'olam tzarich lo hayu ovdim harei hu mevatlah.
No, if it was something that people, the world didn't need, God
would destroy it. הרי הן עובדים לחמה
ולבנה לכוכבים ולמזלות. harei hen ovdim lachamah ulevanah lakochavim ulemazalos. יאבד עולמו
מפני השוטים? ye'aved olamo mipnei hashotim? Would God destroy his world because
of the idiots? אלא עולם כמנהגו נוהג. ela olam keminhago noheg. So
the world goes like its natural course. There's a bigger point here,
which is a deeper theological point. It's not just like, yes, God
would do it, but there's this technical problem and that technical problem
and so on. There's a bigger point here. God lets the world
run by natural laws and God does not get involved in the
details, even if things are going on in the world that
are against God's will. God allows us to shape the world. That's
a very important principle for רמב"ם, Rambam, who for the rationalist, that
God is not going to interfere with miracles, but sets the laws
of nature in course and lets the world run. Okay, ושוטים שקלקלו
עתידין ליתן את הדין, veshotim shekilkelu atidin litein es hadin, and those
idiots that corrupted and did badly, they'll eventually pay for it. דבר
אחר, davar acher, another answer. הרי שגזל סאה של חטים והלך וזרעה
בקרקע, harei shegazal sa shel chittin vehalach vezara'ah bekarka, let's say somebody
stole a measure of wheat and planted it, דינו
שלא תצמח, dinu shelo tizmacha, from a moral perspective, the wheat shouldn't
sprout forth.
אלא, so why does God create a world that doesn't run on
the laws of morality? Like naturally, morality doesn't—I mean, maybe even karma,
you believe it does eventually—but anyway,
but it runs on the laws of nature. אלא עולם כמנהגו נוהג
והולך ושוטים שקלקלו עתידין ליתן את הדין. ella olam keminhago noheig veholach
veshotim shekilkelu atidin litein es hadin. Same point. דבר אחר, davar acher,
another point. הרי שבא על אשת חבירו, harei sheba al eishess chaveiro,
that's another example.
Somebody had intercourse with somebody else's wife. דינו שלא תתעבר, dinu shelo
tite'aber, so that sin should not lead to something, produce something, she
shouldn't get pregnant. אלא עולם כמנהגו נוהג ושוטים שקלקלו עתידין ליתן את
הדין. ella olam keminhago noheig veshotim shekilkelu atidin litein es hadin. Same
point. God allows the world to work by natural law and those
who sin will eventually pay for it. והיינו דאמר ריש לקיש, vehainu
de'amar Reish Lakish, that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says. אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא, amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, לא דיין לרשעים שעושים צלמי פומבי,
lo dayan leresha'im she'osim tzalmi pumbi, it's not enough that these wicked
people go ahead and they make
my image, the divine image, that they make it like
פומבי, pumbi, sort of means public, but it also means like הפקר,
hefker, like just they don't treat it with respect. Okay, it's not
enough that they don't treat my image with respect, meaning the human
being, אלא שמטריחין אותי ומחתימין אותי על כרחי. ella shematrichin osai umachtimin
osi al korchi. Okay,
but they force my hand, meaning they go ahead and they have
sex with their neighbor's wives and they don't care where they're sort
of spreading their
seed and so on, and they don't have the respect of like
the human being, and then they force me to participate in it
and to go ahead and to give
this fetus a צלם אלקים. tzelem Elokim. Okay, so which is like
a really fascinating, it's almost like it's more than עולם כמנהגו נוהג.
olam keminhago noheig. It's like God allows himself even, like it's speaking
about the poignancy about the way that God letting the world work
can sometimes go against God's will, but that's how God has set
it up. Okay, so we will end right over here.